A Finding Aid to the Stanton Macdonald-Wright Papers, 1890-2008, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Stanton Macdonald-Wright papers
1890-2008
Archives of American Art
Macdonald-Wright, Stanton, 1890-1973
AAA.macdstan
Archival Resource Key
17.2 Linear feet
The papers of Southern California painter Stanton Macdonald-Wright measure 17.2 linear feet and date from 1890 to 2008. The collection contains biographical material including address books and interview transcripts; correspondence with family, friends, and artists, including Morgan Russell, and his wife Suzanne Binon, Michel and Suzanne Seuphor, Ann and John Summerfield, and Bethany Wilson; contracts, correspondence, and other material related to exhibitions Macdonald-Wright participated in or that featured his works in the decades following his death; notes, drafts and manuscripts for books, and other writings; diaries and travel journals; invoices, inventories, legal and estate documents, and other personal business records; scrapbooks consisting of clippings and exhibition materials; clippings, exhibition announcements, exhibition catalogs, and other printed materials; sketches and other artwork; photographs, slides and transparencies of Macdonald-Wright, family portraits, travels, and artwork.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 10 series.
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1909-2008 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1907-2005 (1.7 linear feet; Boxes 1-2)
Series 3: Exhibition Files, 1941-2005 (0.2 linear feet; boxes 2-3)
Series 4: Writings, 1913-2003 (4.7 linear feet; Boxes 3-7)
Series 5: Diaries, 1909-1991 (1.5 linear feet; Boxes 7-9)
Series 6: Personal Business Records, 1946-2006 (1.3 linear feet; Boxes 9-10)
Series 7: Scrapbooks, 1910-1994 ( 0.3 linear feet; Boxes 10, 19)
Series 8: Printed Material, 1912-2002 (1.8 linear feet; Boxes 10-12, 19)
Series 9: Artwork, circa 1897-1970 (0.2 linear feet; Boxes 12, 19)
Series 10: Photographic Material, 1890-2004 (5.3 linear feet; Boxes 12-18, OV 20)
Biographical / Historical
Stanton Macdonald-Wright (1890-1973) was the creator of a modernist style of painting based on pure spectral color known as chromatic abstraction or "Synchromism." He worked in New York and later primarily in Los Angeles.
Stanton Macdonald-Wright was born in 1890 in Charlottesville, Virginia. In 1900 the family moved to Santa Monica, California where they ran a seaside hotel. A few years later he took courses at the Art Students League in Los Angeles, studying under Warren T. Huges. His older brother was Willard Huntington Wright, a respected art critic who wrote Modern Painting: Its Tendency and Meaning (1915), upon which he collaborated with his younger brother Stanton, and The Future of Painting (1923), and later became a detective novelist under the name S. S. Van Dine.
At the age of seventeen, Stanton Macdonald-Wright married his first wife and moved to Paris where he immersed himself in European art and studied at the Sorbonne, the Académie Julian, the École des Beaux-Arts, and the Académie Colarossi. While in Europe he also befriended fellow American painter Morgan Russell and the two artists began working closely together. They studied with Canadian painter Percyval Tudor-Hart between 1911 and 1913 and were deeply influenced by their teacher's color theory, which connected the qualities of color to those of music. Together Macdonald-Wright and Russell developed a style of painting based on color and named it "Synchromism." They introduced their work in 1913 at the Der Neue Kuntsalon in Munich and in Paris at the Galerie Bernheim-Jeune. These exhibitions helped to establish Synchromism as an major influence in modern art well into the 1920s.
Stanton Macdonald-Wright and Morgan Russell returned to the United States eager to promote their work and theory. It was not long before the two separated, but both continued to work in the Synchromist style. Together, they held one more Synchromist exhibition in New York in 1916 which received significant critical support. Macdonald-Wright also participated in the prestigious 1916 "Forum Exhibition of Modern American Painters" in New York and exhibited his work at Alfred Stieglitz's famed 291 gallery in New York in 1917. Yet, financial success evaded him.
Macdonald-Wright moved to Santa Monica in 1918, where he taught and served as director of the Los Angeles Art Students League. In 1924 he published his instructive Treatise on Color. In 1927 he organized another joint exhibition with Morgan Russell at the Los Angeles County Museum of Art, where he also exhibited five years later. He exhibited at the Oakland Art Gallery, the California Palace of the Legion of Honor in San Francisco, Alfred Stieglitz's An American Place gallery in New York, and the Stendahl Galleries in Los Angeles. From 1935 to 1942 Macdonald-Wright served as director of the Works Progress Administration's Federal Art Project for Southern California, followed by a faculty position at the University of Southern California at Los Angeles where he taught for sixteen years.
In the late 1950s, Macdonald-Wright completed the Synchome Kineidoscope, a color and light projecting machine first envisioned by Macdonald-Wright and Morgan Russell as early as 1913.
Macdonald-Wright traveled extensively throughout the 1960s and early 1970s, spending time in Hawaii, Italy, and Japan. Macdonald-Wright married three times and died in California in 1973, at the age of 83.
This biographical note draws heavily on the Archives of American Art's West Coast Regional Collector Paul Karlstrom's collection description written upon acquisition of the papers.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing born-digital records or audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Existence and Location of Copies
Materials lent for microfilming are available on 35 mm microfilm reels LA1 and LA5 at Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Stanton Macdonald-Wright first loaned materials to the Archives of American Art for microfilming in 1964. David Nellis, a gallery owner, gave the Archives the artist's unpublished autobiography in 1978. The bulk of the Stanton Macdonald-Wright papers were donated to the Archives of American Art by his widow, Jean Macdonald-Wright, in 2 installments in 1995 and then in 2019 as a bequest.
Related Materials
The Archives of American Art holds several collections related to the Stanton Macdonald-Wright papers. There is an oral interview of Stanton Macdonald-Wright conducted 1964 Apr. 13-Sept. 16, by Betty Hoag. There are also Stanton Macdonald-Wright Letters to Alan and Fanny Leslie, the Stanton Macdonald-Wright Collection of photographs, Stanton Macdonald-Wright Letters to Morgan Russell, Walter Houk Letters from Stanton Macdonald-Wright, and an Oral History of Stanton Macdonald-Wright by Jeanne M. Marshall for the Voice of America Conducted in 1967.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Southern California painter Stanton Macdonald-Wright measure 17.2 linear feet and date from 1890 to 2008. The collection contains biographical material including address books and interview transcripts; correspondence with family, friends, and artists, including Morgan Russell, and his wife Suzanne Binon, Michel and Suzanne Seuphor, Ann and John Summerfield, and Bethany Wilson; contracts, correspondence, and other material related to exhibitions MacDonald-Wright participated in or that featured his works in the decades following his death; notes, drafts and manuscripts for books, and other writings; diaries and travel journals; invoices, inventories, legal and estate documents, and other personal business records; scrapbooks consisting of clippings and exhibition materials; clippings, exhibition announcements, exhibition catalogs, and other printed materials; sketches and other artwork; photographs, slides and transparencies of MacDonald-Wright, family portraits, travels, and artwork.
Biographical material consists of address books, interview transcripts, and obituary and funeral material.
Correspondence consists of letters with family, friends, and artists, including Morgan Russell, and his wife Suzanne Binon, Michel and Suzanne Seuphor, Ann and John Summerfield, and Bethany Wilson.
Exhibition files consists of contracts, correspondence, and some printed material related to exhibitions that Macdonald-Wright participated in or that has featured his works in the decades following his death. Some of the exhibitions include the Southern California Art Project, Kineidoscope film, and "Color and Myth: Stanton MacDonald-Wright and Syncronism."
Writings consist of drafts of essays, plays, and book manuscripts. There are drafts of A Treatise on Color with palettes and color wheels, The Basis of Culture, and Macdonald-Wright's autobiography Bittersweet: An Artist's Life. At the end of the series are a number of files containing photographs, printed material, and some notes that Macdonald-Wright used for various book projects.
Diaries consist of a number of diaries and travel journals. One diary was written in Paris in 1909 in which Macdonald-Wright muses over the aesthetics of art and his color theories. Five additional disbound diaries cover his life from 1939-1973. Travel diaries date from 1959-1972 and cover trips to Italy, Japan, and Hawaii.
Personal business records consists of inventory cards and lists, invoices, property records, and legal documents related to the Macdonald-Wright estate. Also included are files between the estate and various galleries, such as the Esther Robles Gallery and the Goldfield Galleries, in regards to donations of works of art during both his active career and by his estate in the years after his death.
Scrapbooks consist of a scrapbook related to exhibitions featuring MacDonald-Wright's works and scrapbooks of clipping.
Printed material includes a copy of Les Synchromistes exhibition catalog, a newspaper clipping, and The Future of Painting by Willard Wright. Artwork consists of blueprints for Macdonald-Wright's Synchrome Kineidoscope, a color and light projecting machine first envisioned by Macdonald-Wright and Morgan Russell as early as 1913 and finally completed in the late 1950s. Also included are newpaper and magazine clipping, exhibition announcements, and exhibition catalogs.
Artwork consists of a sketchbook, and a number of sketches and drawings.
Photographic material consists of photographs of Stanton Macdonald-Wright and portraits and photographs of his family. Among these photographs is a glass plate negative of his family coat-of-arms. Also included are photographs, slides and transparencies of travels to Japan and Hawaii, and of Macdonald-Wright's artwork. There are also five glass plate images of some of Macdonald-Wright's paintings.
Separated Materials
The Archives of American Art also holds material lent for microfilming (reels LA 1 and LA 5) including a brochure on the Santa Monica Library murals and six photographs of the panels while in Macdonald-Wright's studio. There is also a 1939 exhibition catalog for "Southern California Art Project" a master's thesis on Macdonald-Wright by Dori Jean Watson (1957), and one scrapbook of photographs, clippings, and other printed materials dating from circa 1910-1964. Lent materials were returned to the lender and are not described in the collection container inventory.
Painters -- California -- Los Angeles; Synchromism (Art); Painting, Abstract; Diaries; Scrapbooks; Drawings; Russell, Morgan, 1886-1953; Seuphor, Michel, 1901-1999; Summerfield, Anne, 1917-; Summerfield, John, 1917-
- Biographical Material, 1909-2008; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical material consists of address books, interview transcripts, and obituary and funeral material.
  - Address Books, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Biographies and Chronologies, circa 1967-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Certificates, Licenses, and Identification, 1914-1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Family Records, 1909, 1933-1949, 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Stanton Macdonald-Wright and Elizabeth Hertz Interview Transcript, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Interview Transcripts, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Obituary and Funeral Program, 1973, 2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, circa 1907-2005; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 1.7 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Correspondence consists of letters with family, friends, and artists, including Morgan Russell, and his wife Suzanne Binon, Michel and Suzanne Seuphor, Ann and John Summerfield, and Bethany Wilson.
  - Archives of American Art, 1969-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Jules Barthoux, 1958-circa 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Thomas H. Benton, 1949-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Albert Duveen and Robert Graham, 1957-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Ilene Susan Fort, 1995-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Rose Fried and Rose Fried Gallery, 1964-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Gordon B. Groff and Family, 1970-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
  - Andre Jaqendorf, 1917, 1953-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Clifton Karhu, 1964-1973, 1999-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Alan and Fannie Leslie, 1970, 1994-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Los Angeles, 1978-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - DAvid Nellis "Poison Pen Letters", 1977-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - North Carolina Museum of Art, 1997-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
  - Edyth Polster, 1973-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Henry Reed, 1973-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Esther and Robert Robles and Esther Robles Gallery, 1964-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Morgan Russell, 1920-1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29-34)
  - Morgan Russell, 1923-circa 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
  - Morgan and Suzanne (Binon) Russell, circa 1952-circa 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Miclori and Douglas Scott, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Michel and Suzanne Seuphor, 1954-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - Randy Sprout, 1977, 2004-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Ann and John Summerfield, circa 1965-circa 1972, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Maurice Tuchman, 1977, 2004-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - John Tuska, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - H. J. Weeks, 1973-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Whitney Museum of Art, 1946, 1976-1979, 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Bethany Wilson, circa 1963-circa 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15-21)
  - Archibald and Annie Wright, circa 1907-1915; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22-24)
  - Linfa Riza Wright, 1934-1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Willard Wright, 1913-1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26-28)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, A-R, 1924-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, S-Z, 1918-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1942-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31-32)
- Exhibition Files, 1941-2005; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Boxes 2-3
  Exhibition files consists of contracts, correspondence, and some printed material related to exhibitions that Macdonald-Wright participated in or that has featured his works in the decades following his death. Some of the exhibitions include the Southern California Art Project, Kineidoscope film, and "Color and Myth: Stanton MacDonald-Wright and Syncronism."
  - Southern California Art Project, Work Projects Administration, 1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - US Educational Commission in Japan, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Permissions, 1970-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Retrospective Checklist, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Ancestral Mask Trilogy, 2000-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - "Color and Myth: Stanton MacDonald-Wright and Syncronism" Exhibition, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Kineidoscope Film Permissions, 2003-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - "Color Myth, & Music" Retrospective, 2001; Archival Resource Key; 2 Electronic discs (CD) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Disc 1 is labeled, "Stanton MacDonald Wright (Retrospective) Color, Myth, & Music." Disc 2 is labeled, "Stanton-MacDonald-Wright Color, Myth, & Music Retrospective (Finalized)."
  - "On Ramps: Transitional Moments in California Art" Exhibition, 2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "Musique et Arts Plastiques au 20 Siecle" Exhibition, 2002-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "Visual Music, 1905-2005" Exhibition, 2004-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Los Angeles County Museum of Art, 2002-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "Sons et Lumieres" Exhibition, 2002-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Writings, 1913-2003; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 4.7 Linear feet Boxes 3-7
  Writings consist of drafts of essays, plays, and book manuscripts. There are drafts of A Treatise on Color with palettes and color wheels, The Basis of Culture, and Macdonald-Wright's autobiography Bittersweet: An Artist's Life. At the end of the series are a number of files containing photographs, printed material, and some notes that Macdonald-Wright used for various book projects.
  - Writings on Art, 1913-circa 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7-21)
  - "The Alliance Between Music and the Other Arts", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - "And After the Moderns?", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - "The Ancestral Mask" Drafts, Notes, and Reviews, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Notes and Writings, Art and Philosophy, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - "Art and the Topical", 1934; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - "A Basis of Culture" Drafts, Notes, and Revisions, circa 1933, circa 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 27-37)
  - "Beyond Aesthetics" Drafts, Notes, and Revisions, 1930, 1973, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 38-40)
  - "Beyond Aesthetics" Drafts, Notes, and Revisions, circa 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1-11)
  - Bedside Notes, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - "Bittersweet: An Artist's Life", circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 13-15)
  - "Clair de Lune" Drafts, Notes, and Revisions, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 16-21)
  - Color Wheels and Charts, circa 1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 22-23)
  - Cycle Charts, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Essays on Art, circa 1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - "The Rebirth of the Classic Impulse", 1920; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - A Footnote to the Macdonald Wright Story, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - "Four Fantastic Satires", circa 1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 28)
    Only contains 3 of the satires.
  - Haikus, 1971-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Haiku Notebook, 1962-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Harmony, circa 1920-1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Hellenism, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Hellenism, 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "Herodiade" Poem by Willard Wright, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Kinetic Synchronism Chapter, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Kineidscope Notes, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Literary Works, circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - "Modernist Art and the American Field", circa 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Observations, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "Official Art", circa 1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Partial Elizabeth Hertz Manuscript, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Poetry, circa 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Road to Valhalla Statements, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - "Serenade in Blue" Drafts. Notes, and Revisions, circa 1963, circa 1973, circa 2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 12-19)
  - "Some Aspects of Sung Paintings", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Synchrome Kineidoscope Diagrams, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - "Stanton MacDonald-Wright and Synchronism", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - "Synchronism: An Overview" Chapter Draft by Will South, 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - "Three Meals a Day, Not Four" by Debbie Zambianco, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - "Towards a Visual Music and Other Writings" by William Moritz, circa 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - "Treatise on Color", 1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 26-27)
  - "Vanderveer" by Willard Huntington Wright, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 28-29)
  - Book Drafts, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 30-31)
  - List of Works for Book Project, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Book Reference Material, circa 1975-circa 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 33-44)
  - Book Reference Material, circa 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 1-5)
  - Book Project, "Art-The Life of Creation", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 6-13)
  - Book Project, "Serenade in Blue", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 14-16)
  - Book Project, Draft, Notes, and Revisions, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 1-5)
  - Handwritten Draft of Untitled Manuscript, circa 1920-circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Typescript Draft of Untitled Manuscript, circa 1920-circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Draft Typescript Pages, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - "The Structure of Art", circa 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Stanton Macdonald-Wright Recorded Remarks, 1962-1970; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 7, Folder 10)
    Tape 1, Side 1 labeled, "SMW recording for Sm. Stanton. Tape of Visit in August 1970 at his Pac. Palisades home." Tape 1, Side 2 labeled, "Continuation of '70 visit. Voices of SMW, Jean, Tamara, Bethany, Stanton, & Junior."
    Tape 2 is unlabeled.
  - Stanton Macdonald-Wright Bibliography, circa 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Lectures, 1929-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 12-16)
  - Notes for Art History Classes, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 17-18)
  - Notes for Hexagrams, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 19-20)
  - Notes, Jean MacDonald-Wright, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Notes, Japan, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Notes, circa 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 22-24)